Register of the Basil M. Bensin Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Basil M. Bensin papers
1913-1970
2001C60
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, biographical data, and photographs, relating to agriculture, especially in northern climates, and to Russian émigré affairs.
Bensin, Basil M.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
B. M. Bensin was born in Russia on 30 January 1881 (O. S.). He received his education in agricultural sciences at the University of Minnesota, graduating with an M.S. in 1912. Returning to Russia, he authored a pamphlet entitled Izuchenie zasukhoustoichivykh ras sel'sko-khoziaistvennykh rastenii in 1913. After 1920, he emigrated to Czechosovakia, where he published Sel'skoe khoziaistvo i kooperatsiia v S.-Amerikie (Prague, 1923) and Shkola i sel'skoe khoziaistvo (Prague, 1924).
Coming to the United States in 1930, he continued his agricultural researches: as an agronomist for the Alaska Agricultural Experiment Station and instructor at the University of Alaska from 1945 to 1948, he identified strains of plants capable of withstanding the extreme cold and harsh climate of the region. Bensin was also active in the Russian émigré Sokol movement, and his collection contains some materials on that topic. He died in North Carolina in February 1973.
Biographical Note
1881 January 30 (O.S.) Born, Russia
1912 M. S., Agricultural Sciences, University of Minnesota Returned to Russia
1913 Author, Izuchenie zasukhoustoichivykh ras sel'sko-khoziaistvennykh rastenii
1923 Author, Sel'skoe khoziaistvo i kooperatsiia v S.-Amerikie
1924 Author, Shkola i sel'skoe khoziaistvo
1930 Arrived in the United States
1945-1948 Agronomist, Alaska Agricultural Experiment Station Instructor, University of Alaska
Scope and Content Note
Basil M. Benzin (Vasilii Mitrofanovich Benzin) was an agricultural expert active in Russia (to 1920), Czechoslovakia (1921-1930) and the United States (1910-1912 and 1930 to his death). The collection includes his written works on varioua aspects of agronomy and its economic organization, as well as a file of unique materials on the history of Russian Sokol organizations in Europe and the United States (SUBJECT FILE/Athletic clubs). Also interesting are the files on his son's (Igor Bensen) career as an engineer for General Electric and inventor of flying contraptions (BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Family file/Bensen, Igor, and PHOTOGRAPHS/Bensen, Igor).
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Agriculture.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1945-1951 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Articles, award, bibliographies, clippings and family file, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Articles about B. M. Bensin. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes entry from International Who's Who, 1948 June
  - Award (Folder 1: 2)
  - Bibliographies of works published (Folder 1: 3)
  - Clippings about or mentioning B. M. Bensin (Folder 1: 4)
  - Family file
    - Bensen, Igor Vasil'evich (son). (Folder 1: 5)
      General note
      See also PHOTOGRAPHS
      Biographical materials.
    - Benzin, A. M. (brother?). (Folder 1: 6)
      Clipping and description of his inventions
- Correspondence, 1970 (Folder 1: 7)
  One greeting card sent to N. A. Slobodchikov
- Speeches and Writings, 1913-1952 (Box 1)
  Articles and books, arranged chronologically by title
  - "Agricultural Self-Sufficiency Possible in Alaska," Ketchikan Alaska Chronicle, n.d. (Folder 1: 8)
    Printed copy
  - "Agroecology: Basic Science of Agriculture,", n.d. (Folder 1: 9)
    Typescript
  - "Arctic Coldframes with Miracle Solar Reflectors for Northern Climates,", n.d. (Folder 1: 10)
  - "Arctic Solar Reflectors for Northern Climates,", n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
  - "K istorii vozniknoveniia i razvitiia nauki agroekologii,", n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
    Holograph
  - "'Russkii sokol:' Ego zadachi i tsieli v Amerikie,", n.d. (Folder 1: 13)
  - Izuchenie zasukhoustoichivykh ras sel'sko-khoziaistvennykh rastenii, 1913 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Sel'skoe khoziaistvo i kooperatsiia v S.-Amerikie, 1923 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Shkola i sel'skoe khoziaistvo, 1924 (Folder 1: 16)
  - "O siemenakh i o posievie," and "Zasukhi i neurozhai v Rossii," Kalendar' dlia russkikh zemlediel'tsev na 1925 god (Folder 1: 17)
  - "Polevyia kul'tury Iuga i Iugo-Vostoka Rossii," Kalendar' dlia russkikh zemlediel'tsev na 1926 god (Folder 1: 18)
  - "Agroecological Studies of Maize Plant," Program of a lecture, 1930 (Folder 1: 19)
  - "Agroecological Exploration in the Soto La Marina Region, Mexico," The Geographical Review, 1935 April (Folder 1: 20)
  - "The Future of Orthodoxy in America," Russian Orthodox Journal, 1945 (Folder 1: 21)
  - "Problems of Agricultural Microclimatology in Alaska," Farthest North Collegian, 1950 March (Folder 1: 22)
  - "Agroecological World Geography," Biologia, 1951 (Folder 1: 23)
  - "Growing Warm Season Vegetables in Alaska,"., 1951 May (Folder 1: 24)
  - "Arctic Cold Frames for Northern Climates,"., 1952 (Folder 1: 25)
  - "Coal Dust for Alaskan Gardens,"., 1952 (Folder 1: 26)
  - "Warm Season Vegetables in Alaska,"., 1952 (Folder 1: 27)
- Subject File, 1924-1937 (Box 1)
  Clippings, receipt and printed matter arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Alaska. (Folder 1: 28)
    Travel guides, brochures, railroad timetables, and receipt from Bensin's travels
  - Athletic clubs. (Folder 1: 29)
    Materials on Czech and Russian Sokol organizations in Czechoslovakia and the United States
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 1)
  Three prints of B. M. Bensin and five of Igor Bensen and his gyrocopters
  - Bensin, B. M. (Folder 1: 30)
    Three prints
  - Bensen, Igor V. (Folder 1: 31)
    Five prints of him and his gyrocopters